Guide to the Andrei Voznesenskii Papers
Department of Special Collections
- Series 1: Manuscripts
  - Subseries 1.2: Leaves
    - Subsubseries 1.2.2: Prose
      - "Virtual'nye vitrazhi" [4 of 6]n.d., An annotated typescript, pages 299-406, some are damaged. (Box 14, Folder 22)
        Ivan Tsvetaev; Michelangelo Buonarroti; Donato Bramante; Ivan Zholtovskii; Natalia Golovina; Vladimir Maiakovskii; Maksimilian Voloshin; Jean Cocteau; Pablo Picasso; Aleksandr Pushkin; Osip Mandel'shtam; Henri Michaux [Anri Miso]; Jean Cocteau; Dante Alighieri; Alessandro de Medici; Gavriil [Gavrila] Derzhavin; Francesco Petrarca; Girolamo Savonarola; TommasoCavalieri; Pietro Aretino; Boris Pasternak; Anatolii Efros; Dmitrii Shostakovich; Renato Guttuso; Cesare Guasti; Francesco Berni; Thomas Mann; Salvador Dali; Vladimir Lenin; Adolf Hitler; Nikita Khrushchev; Andre Breton; Louis Aragon; Paul Éluard; Max Ernst; Nikolai Gogol'; Diego Rodriges de Silva Velaskes [Rodrigez de Silva Velasquez]; Johannes Vermeer; Raffaello Sanzio [Raffaello Santi; Raffaello de Urbino; Rafael Sanzio de Urbino]; Henry Moore; Roberto Sebastian Echaurren Matta; Jean-Jacque Mari [?]; Vladimir Vysotskii; Jean-Auguste-Dominique Ingres [?]; Genrikh Sapgir; Igor' Kholin; Igor' Irteniev; Vladimir Sorokin; Mikhail Zhvanetskii; Semen Nadson; Martin Heidegger; Ol'ga Sedakova; Roy Lichtenstein; Guillaume Apollinaire; Robert Lowell; David Samoilov; Gala Dali; Allen Ginsberg; F.Zbarskii; Vasilii Kandinskii; Kazimir Malevich; Paul Klee; Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn; Konstantin Mel'nikov; Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis; Shamil Basaiev [Basayev]; Marc [Mark] Chagall [Shagall]; Charles-Edouard Jeanneret [Le Corbusier]; Bartolomeo Franchesko Rastrelli; Father Pavel Florenskii; I.D.Mel'chakov; Aleksei Shchusev; Mikhail Vrubel'; Vasilii Rozanov; Nina Kandinskaia; Martin Luther; S.P.Kapitsa; N.Kozyrev; Andjei Vaida; Henri Moore; Laurence Olivier; Gaius Iulius Cesar; Peter I; Iurii Liubimov; Ella Levina; Sergei Esenin; L.O.Badalian; Liudmila Tselikovskaia; Aleksandr Mitta; Zurab Tsereteli; Vsevolod Abdulov; Bulat Okudzhava; Oleg Tabakov; Veniamin Smekhov; Valerii Zolotukhin; Boris Khmel'nitskii; Bella Akhmadulina; Zoia Boguslavskaia; Iurii Trifonov; Alla Demidova; Gosha Roninson; Leonid Filatov; Maiia Plisetskaia; Rodion Shchedrin; Mikael Tariverdiev; Thomas Stearns Eliot; Dylan Thomas; Stephen Spender; Bob Dylan; John Lennon; Pablo Neruda; Boris Anrep; Anna Akhmatova; Lawrence Ferlinghetti; Isaiah Berlin; Albert Einstein; Dmitrii Likhachev; Charlie Chaplin; Winston Churchill; Denis Davydov; Anton Del'vig; Marina Tsvetaeva; John Russell [?]; Dmitrii Shostakovich; Sergei Prokofiev; Igor' Stravinskii; Aram Khachaturian; Francois Villon; John Roberts; Francisco Goya; Marilyn Monroe; Edgar Degas [Hilaire-Germain-]; Paul Ce;zanne; Alberto Giacometti; Alberto Giacometti; Johann Wolfgang von Goethe; Leonid Pavlov; Boris Godunov; Napoleon Bonaparte; Anna Pavlova; Petr Chaikovskii; Aleksandr Blok; Frederick Chopin; William Shakespeare; Mikhail Lermontov; Sergei Eisenstein; Viktor Vasnetsov; Kapitolina Afanasieva; Anna Dostoevskaia; Liudmila Zykina; Georgii Daneliia; Andrei Belyi; Sergei [?] Tupolev; Sergei Ilyushin; Lev Tolstoi.; Moskovskii teatr dramy i komedii na Taganke.
      - "Virtual'nye vitrazhi" [5 of 6]n.d., An annotated typescript, pages 407-449, some are damaged. (Box 14, Folder 23)
        Incl. essays: "Iz 'Ozy' ", "Temnaia figura", "Khranitel' ognia", "Nebom edinym", "Berestianaia kniga i granitnaia", "Kabbalisticheskaia ekspertiza", "Casino 'Rossiia' " (a fragment), "Oglavlenie" (the list of content), and an interview "Razbeite illiuzii".
        Garry Kasparov; Ekaterina II [Catherine the Great]; Caligula; Vasilii Aksenov; Mukhail Pozdniaev; Anna Akhmatova; Frederick [Fryderyk] Chopin; Mikhail Chigorin; Makhmud Esambaev; Vladimir Nabokov; Marcel Duchamp [Dushan]; Francois-Andre; Danican Philidor [Filidor]; Mata Hari; Elton John; Sting; Ivan the Terrible; Gata Kamskii [Kamsky]; Klaudia Shiffer; Bobby Fischer; Antonio Stradivari; Afanasii Fet [Shenshin]; Ekaterina II; Kazimir Malevich; Aleksandr Pushkin; Nikolai Gogol'; Iosif Stalin; Grigorii Zinoviev; Aleksei Rykov; Semen Budennyi; Eduard Radzinskii; Petr Chaikovskii; Fedor Dostoevskii; Lev Tolstoi; Ermak; Sviatoslav Belza; Oleg Kulik; Garik Sukachev; Pierre Cardin; Pablo Picasso; Nikita Khrushchev; Allen Ginsberg; Inna Churikova; Napoleon Bonaparte; Liubov' Orlova; Vladimir Lenin; Nils Bor [Bohr]; Franz Shubert; Velimir Khlebnikov; Sergei Kurekhin; Nina Iskrenko; Aleksandr Iakovlev; Leonardo da Vinci; Feliks Iusupov; Leonid Martynov; Gavriil [Gavrila] Derzhavin; Evgenii Baratynskii; Nikolai Zabolotskii; Mokambet; Boris Pasternak; Federico García Lorca; John Keats; Rainer Maria Rilke; Shandor Petefi [Sándor Petöfi]; Robert Lowell; Pele; [Edson Arantes Do Nascimento]; Martin Luther; Johann Wolfgang von Goethe; Nikolai [?] Kholodkovskii; Gustave Dore;; Leonardo da Vinci; Wiiliam Shakespeare; Martin Heidegger; Theodor Adorno; Herman Cohen; Bulat Okudzhava; Jacob and Wilhelm Grimm; Paul Klee; Vladimir Maiakovskii; Konstantin Sluchevskii; Aleksandr Blok; Mikhail Lermontov; Eduard Bagritskii; Sergei Esenin; Osip Mandel'shtam; Iurii Liubimov; Andrei Rublev; Dionisii; George Gordon Byron; John Keats; Percy Bysshe Shelley; Nikolai Gogol'; Nadia Le;ger; Aleksandr Liberman; Tatiana Liberman [Iakovleva]; Fedor Demin-Blagoveshchenskii; Aleksei Kozlov; Andrei Makarevich; V.Vittikh; G.Lukianov; Bob Holman; Bill Adler; Arkadii Demin-Blagoveshchenskii; Valerian Kuibyshev; Roland Barthes; Igal' [Yigal] Amir; David Kav; Aleksandr Libin; Yitzhak Rabin; Shimon Peres; Robert Kennedy; Shema Prins; Natan Zakh; David Avidan; Aleksandr Gol'dshtein; Nelli Gutina; Liudmila Tselikovskaia; Aleksandr Voronel'; Vladimir Vysotskii; Ezra Pound; Mikhail Grobman; Aleksei Kruchenykh; Irina Vrubel'-Golubkina; Mikhail L'vov; Zakhar Sherman; Andrei Tarkovskii; Evgenii Kolobov; Nina Ananiashvili; Vladimir Spivakov; Mstislav Rostropovich; Galina Vishnevskaia; Pavel Stepanov; Pierre Cardin; Arthur Rimbaud.; Moskovskii teatr dramy i komedii na Taganke.
      - "Virtual'nye vitrazhi" [6 of 6]1971; n.d., Annotated typewritten and handwritten drafts, 98 pages total, mostly damaged. (Box 14, Folder 24)
        Miscellaneous fragments of essays, including previous variants. Incl., among others: "Giunter Grass", "Lebedinyi rubanok", "Apel'siny, apel'siny...", "Usy 'Zemlemer' ", "Art", "Klassik", "Krestnaia krestnitsa", "Chelovek s drevesnym imenem", "Taganka-antitiur'ma", "Ledianoe plamia", "Stikhotvorenie v pereulke", "Kabbalisticheskaia ekspertiza", "Virtual'nye nezabudki" (with "Oglavlenie" and "Nadpisi pod risunki"), "Vsenarodnyi Volodia", "Berestianaia kniga i granitnaia", "Iazyk kak pokaz", "Zub razuma", "Khamiashchie khameleony", "Sud'baby", "Virtual'naia klaviatura", mostly incomplete.
        Günter Grass; Vasilii Kazin; Stepan Shchipachev; Giangiacomo Feltrinelli; Nina Iskrenko; Arthur Miller; Boris Pasternak; Iurii Liubimov; Vladimir Vysotskii; Konstantin Mel'nikov; Martin Heidegger; Marc [Mark] Chagall [Shagall]; Sviatoslav Richter; Fedor Demin-Blagoveshchenskii; Valentin Kataev.; Moskovskii teatr dramy i komedii na Taganke.
      - "Vizual'naia forma dukhovnoi poezii"n.d., An annotated typescript, 3 pages, slightly damaged. (Box 15, Folder 1)
        Boris Pasternak; Boris Yeltsyn; Vladimir Zhirinovskii; Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn; Ernst Neizvestnyi; Il'ia Glazunov; Petr Chaikovskii; Ludwig van Beethoven; Vasilii Kandinskii; Osip Mandel'shtam; Sviatoslav Fedorov; Iosif Stalin; Nikita Khrushchev; Guillaume Apollinaire; Jacques Derrida; Kuzma Petrov-Vodkin; Henri Matisse; Marina Tsvetaeva; Lev Shestov; Vladimir Soloviev; Martin Luther; Sergei Esenin; Father Pavel Florenskii.
      - "Vmesto poslesloviia": An interview with A.Voznesenskii11.21.2001, An annotated typescript, 7 pages (1 complete copy) and 1 separate page (from another copy), with numerous notes and drafts [?] on the other side, damaged. Incl. also a short handwritten note on a small yellow piece of paper, one separate typewritten page with a fragment of the interview, annotated, covered with Voznesenskii's notes and severely damaged, and a galley copy of the interview, annotated, damaged, incomplete (the end is missing), 3 pages. (Box 15, Folder 2)
        An interview and miscellaneous notes.
        Mikhail Aivazian; Nikita Khrushchev; A.Prokofiev; N.Gribachev; Kazimir Malevich; Eduardas Miezelaitis; A.Cherkizov; Evgenii Yevtushenko; Nikolai Zabolotskii; Alisa LIsetskaia; Anatolii Rybakov; Aleksandr Mezhirov; Nikolai Aseev; Andrei Malyshko; Wystan Hugh Auden; Patricia Blake [?]; V.V. Medvedev; Boris Slutskii.
      - Voznesenskii's talk with the literary critic Vladimir Ognevn.d., Annotated typewritten fragments, 39 pages total, mostly damaged. (Box 15, Folder 3)
        Fragments of the talk.
        Vladimir Ognev; Aleksandr Pushkin; Igor' Stravinskii; Andrei Rublev; Dionisii; Vladimir Maiakovskii; Valentin Serov; Aleksandr Blok; Dmitrii Shostakovich; Petr Chaikovskii; Sergei Rakhmaninov; Alban Berg; Matvei [?] Kazakov; Le Corbusier [Charles Edouard Jeanneret]; Pablo Picasso; Jacqueline Picasso; Lev Oshanin; Johann Wolfgang von Goethe; Aleksei Kruchenykh; Mikhail Vrubel'; Fedor Abramov; Vasilii Aksenov; Chingiz Aitmatov; Vasilii Belov; Vasil' Bykov; David Samoilov; Aleksandr Mezhirov; Konstantin Simonov; Boris Slutskii; Viktor Sosnora; Justinas Marcinkevicius [?]; Petr Chaadaev; Vissarion Belinskii; Francois-Marie Arouet de Voltaire; Iurii Tynianov; Boris Eikhenbaum; Mikhail Lermontov; Aleksandr Polezhaev; Victor Shklovskii; Dante Alighieri; Rembrandt Harmenszoon van Rijn; Vladimir Dal'; Sergei Averintsev; Father Pavel Florenskii; Velimir Khlebnikov; Arkadii Raikin; Sergei Esenin; Henri Matisse; Michelangelo Antonioni; Kuzma Petrov-Vodkin; Franz Marc; Aleksandr Tvardovskii; Leonid Martynov; Vladimir Lenin; Nadezhda Krupskaia; Rodion Shchedrin; Arnold Schönberg; Ivan [?] Kirievskii; Homer; Igor' Severianin; Nikolai Zabolotskii.
      - "Zadurennyi [?] nashei propagandoi..."1998; n.d., Handwritten drafts, 1 A3 piece of paper with numerous handwritten notes, damaged. (Box 15, Folder 4)
        Fragments of an essay [?], numerous handwritten notes made by A.Voznesenskii, and a handwritten note made by Zoia Boguslavskaia [?]: "Andriushiny chernoviki. 1998 g.".
        Nikita Khrushchev; John Kennedy.
    - Subsubseries 1.2.3: Translations
      - "Iadernaia zima" [A translation of Lord Byron's poem "Darkness"]n.d., Several handwritten / typewritten rough drafts with minor corrections, 11 pages total, and an untitled handwritten rough draft of an essay, 2 pages. There are a typewritten copy of a poem, a fragment of a rough draft, and several notes on the other side of some leaves. Some leaves are slightly damaged. (Box 15, Folder 5)
        Drafts of a poem "Iadernaia zima", a poem "Akhillesovo serdtse", a fragment of an essay about the writer Vladimir Soloukhin, and miscellaneous notes.
        Lord George Gordon Byron; Vladimir Soloukhin; Vladimir Maiakovskii; Boris Pasternak; Sergei Esenin; Mary Shelley.
      - "Strofy" [Translations from József Attila]n.d., An annotated typescript, 8 pages, slightly damaged. (Box 15, Folder 6)
        Translations from Hungarian poet József Attila.
        József Attila.
      - Translations from Michelangelo Buonarroti n.d., Twelve annotated typewritten pages, 1 handwritten note (1 page), adn 1 handwritten rough draft (1 page), 14 pages total, some are damaged. (Box 15, Folder 7)
        Translations from Michelangelo Buonarroti. Incl. poems: "Tvorchestvo", "Istina", "Vse nashi slovesa emu - kak dym...", "Liubov' moia, kak ia tebia liubliu!..", "Kogda ia vdrug s toboiu razluchen...", Gnev", "On byl odin zhivoi mezh nezhivykh...", "Figuru 'Noch' v memoriale sna'...", "Konchinu chuiu. No ne znaiu chasa...", "ia schastliv, chto ia umer molodym...", some in several variants. Incl. also a fragment of an essay [?] "Vprochem, bylo li eto dlia Mikelandzhelo 'vul'garnym'?" (the beginning and the end are missing) and a note.
        Michelangelo Buonarroti; Dante Alighieri.
      - Translations from Soviet poets1958, Annotated typewritten drafts, 90 pages total, some are damaged, and a green folder with handwritten notes on it, damaged. (Box 15, Folder 8)
        Translations from Soviet poets Togolok Moldo, Iosif Noneshvili, Ashot Grashi, Sil'va Kaputikian, Magirash Sarikova, and Seifulin Saken.
        Togolok Moldo; Iosif Noneshvili; Ashot Grashi; Sil'va Kaputikian; Magirash Sarikova; Seifulin Saken.
- Series 2: Correspondence
  - Subseries 2.1: Incoming
    - A.I.P., A letter to A.Voznesenskii09.17.1984, An empty posted envelope, slightly damaged. (Box 16, Folder 1)
      An empty posted envelope.
    - Abaidoullina, E., A letter to A.Voznesenskii07.14.1976, A handwritten letter, 1 page, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 2)
      A letter.
      Emma Abaidoullina.
    - Acar, O., A letter to A.Voznesenskii01.12.1994 - 01.05.1997 [?], A fax copy of a typewritten letter with a handwritten signature, 1 page, and a posted envelope. Damaged. (Box 16, Folder 3)
      A letter and an envelope.
      Ozgen Acar.; Cumhuriyel Newspaper.
    - Aivazian [?], M., A letter [?] to A.Voznesenskiin.d., An empty unposted envelope, damaged, with a handwritten draft of a poem [?]. (Box 16, Folder 4)
      An envelope with a draft.
    - Akifiev [?], S., A letter to A.Voznesenskiin.d. [1998-2004 ?], A handwritten letter, 1 page, slightly damaged. (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Alipov, N., A note to A.Voznesenskiin.d., A typewritten note with a handwritten postscriptum and several handwritten notes, 1 page, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 6)
      A typewritten note with a handwritten postscriptum made by N.Alipov and several handwritten notes made by A.Voznesenskii. A text of an interview mentioned in the note is missing.
      Nikolai Alipov.
    - Alla, A letter to A.Voznesenskii10.03.1984, A handwritten letter, 2 pages, and a posted envelope, slightly damaged. (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Alla, Letters to A.Voznesenskii [1 of 5]07.09.1994; n.d., Handwritten letters, some of them incomplete and / or signed with the initial 'A' only, 5 pages, three envelopes, one of them unposted, with a handwritten note, two postal delivery notices, and an invitation pass. Some papers are damaged. (Box 16, Folder 8)
      Letters, a handwritten note mentioning Irina from "Novyi mir", two postal delivery notices to A.Voznesenskii, and an invitation pass to Zoia Boguslavskaia from "Satirikon" Theatre.
      Zoia Boguslavskaia; Varlam Shalamov; Boris Pasternak.; "Satirikon" Theatre.
    - Alla, Letters to A.Voznesenskii [2 of 5]n.d., Handwritten letters, some of them incomplete, 16 pages, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 9)
      Letters.
    - Alla, Letters to A.Voznesenskii [3 of 5]n.d., Handwritten letters, some of them incomplete, 11 pages, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 10)
      Dmitrii Dibrov; Iosif Stalin; Leonid Brezhnev.
    - Alla, Letters to A.Voznesenskii [4 of 5]n.d., Handwritten letters, some of them incomplete, 9 pages, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 11)
      Lev Tolstoi.
    - Alla, Letters to A.Voznesenskii [5 of 5]May 1993; n.d., Handwritten letters, some of them incomplete, 4 pages, damaged, and an annotated typewritten poem, 1 page. (Box 16, Folder 12)
      Letters; a poem "Babushka Vera, razrushen tvoi dom s mezoninom..." by Apollinariia Zueva.
      Apollinariia Zueva.
    - Alla [?] [Anna ?], A postcard to A.Voznesenskiin.d. [December ?], A handwritten postcard. (Box 16, Folder 13)
      A postcard
    - Amram [?], A note to A.Voznesenskii02.27.1965 - 1985 [?], A photocopy of a handwritten letter, 1 page, with a handwritten note. (Box 16, Folder 14)
      A photocopy of a handwritten letter from Jack Ke;rouac to Davey [?] dated 02.27.1965, with a handwritten note from Amram [?] to A.Voznesenskii made "twenty years later".
      Jack Ke;rouac.
    - Andreev, Ia., A letter to A.Voznesenskiin.d., A handwritten letter, 1 page, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 15)
      A letter. A book mentioned in it is missing.
      Iakov Andreev.
    - Andreev, O., A letter to A.Voznesenskiin.d., An official typewritten letter, 1 page, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 16)
      "OOO Klub-restoran TsDL"
    - Andrei, A note to A.Voznesenskiin.d., A typescript with a handwritten note and other handwritten additions, 3 pages, slightly damaged. (Box 16, Folder 17)
      Incl. two poems by Andrei (the last name is illegible) and his note to A.Voznesenskii.
    - Andrei Tarkovsky Foundation, A letter to A.Voznesenskii03.14-21.2000, A fax copy of an official typewritten letter with handwritten signatures and a sketch on the other side, 1 page, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 18)
      Andrei Tarkovskii [Tarkovsky]; N.D.Volkova; I.V.Smolin.; Andrei Tarkovsky Foundation.
    - Ania, A note to A.Voznesenskiin.d., A handwritten note on a small yellow piece of paper, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 19)
      A note.
    - Ania [?], A letter to A.Voznesenskii12.31.1998 - 01.19.1999, A postcard, a posted envelope, and a typescript with handwritten corrections / additions, 5 pages, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 20)
      Poems by Ania [?], an empty postcard, and an envelope.
      Martin Heidegger; Arnold Schwarzenegger.
    - Anna, A note to A.Voznesenskiin.d., A handwritten note on the "Prince Albert Hotel" business card, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 21)
    - Antonova, I.A., A letter to Z.Boguslavskaia and A.Voznesenskii11.11-16.1996, An official typewritten letter with a handwritten signature and a posted envelope, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 22)
      Zoia Boguslavskaia; I.A.Antonova.; Pushkin State Museum of Fine Arts.
    - Antonova, I.A., New Year postcard to A.Voznesenskiin.d. [Dec 1993 - Jan 1994 ?], A typewritten postcard with a handwritten signature. (Box 16, Folder 23)
      A postcard.
      I.A.Antonova.; Pushkin State Museum of Fine Arts.
    - Archinto, R., A letter to A.Voznesenskii02.01.1994, A typewritten letter with a handwritten signature, 1 page, and a posted envelope, slightly damaged. (Box 16, Folder 24)
      Rosellina Archinto.
    - Aridjis, E., Letters to A.Voznesenskii01.12.1999 - 01 [?].03 [?].2002, A postcard with a short handwritten note, two posted envelopes, a typewritten note (without a signature), and a small toy. Damaged. (Box 16, Folder 25)
      A postcard, two envelopes, a note to Dr. Ernesto Zedillo, President of Mexico, concerning the defense of the gray whale, and a small toy.
      Dr. Ernesto Zedillo; Eva Aridjis.
    - Arima, Takashi, A letter to A.Voznesenskii12.14-15.1996; n.d., A handwritten letter, 1 page, two envelopes of different size (one envelope is posted and damaged), and two photos with short handwritten notes on the back. (Box 16, Folder 26)
      A letter, two envelopes, and two photos. A book mentioned in the letter is in Voznesenskii's book collection.
      Takashi Arima.
    - Averov, I., A note to A.Voznesenskii12.28.2001, A handwritten note, 1 page, and a typescript with handwritten additions, incomplete (pages 6-8, 14, 16, 21-26, 28, 30-31, 35, 37, 44-48, 50-56, 58, 60, 66, 68-71, 73-74, 80, 82 are missing), 44 pages. Damaged. (Box 16, Folder 27)
      A note and a typescript "Mera ravnovesiia" (a collection of poems by Igor' Averov).
      Igor' Averov.
    - Avgust, Kseniia, A letter to A.VoznesenskiiMarch 1994 - 04.06.2001; n.d., A handwritten letter, 1 page, slightly damaged, and a typescript, 16 pages. (Box 16, Folder 28)
      A letter and a typescript "Moi mir" (a collection of poems by Kseniia Avgust).
      Kseniia Avgust.
    - B., Sergei, A note to A.Voznesenskii05.08.1996, A handwritten note, 1 page, and an envelope, slightly damaged. (Box 16, Folder 29)
      A note and an envelope. Poems mentioned in the note are missing.
    - Baker, James A., III, Mrs., A letter to A.Voznesenskii03.18.1991, A typewritten letter with a handwritten signature (illegible) and a handwritten addition, 1 page, slightly damaged. (Box 16, Folder 30)
      Mrs. James A. Baker, III; Boris Pasternak.
    - Balashov [?], T., A note to A.Voznesenskii09.02.2001, A handwritten note, 1 page, slightly damaged. (Box 16, Folder 31)
      T.Balashov [?]; Zoia Boguslavskaia; Lilia Brik; Vasilii Katanian.
    - Banchukov, R.V., A letter to A.Voznesenskiin.d. [after 1980], A handwritten letter, 1 page, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 32)
      Boris Chichibabin; Zoia Boguslavskaia; Revold Banchukov; Friedrich Schiller; Johann Wolfgang von Goethe.
    - Barakhovich, A.Ia., A letter to A.Voznesenskii08.24.1996, A damaged fragment of an annotated typescript with a handwritten note in the end, 2 pages. (Box 16, Folder 33)
      A fragment of a typescript and a note.
      Arkadii Barakhovich.
    - Barton [?], [?], A letter to A.Voznesenskii04.11.1994, An official typewritten letter with a handwritten signature, 1 page, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 34)
      The New York Review of Books.
    - Beliaev, M.E., A letter to A.Voznesenskiin.d., A handwritten letter, 1 page, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 35)
      Mikhail Beliaev; Boris Yeltsyn.
    - Bella, A postcard to A.Voznesenskii [?]06.13.1974 [?], An unposted postcard with a handwritten note, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 36)
    - Belova, E., A postcard to A.Voznesenskiin.d., An unposted postcard with a handwritten note. (Box 16, Folder 37)
      Elena Belova; Marina Tsvetaeva.
    - Bel'chikova, L.Ia., Two postcards to A.Voznesenskiin.d., An unposted postcard with a handwritten note and an empty postcard. (Box 16, Folder 38)
      Two postcards, one with a note.
      Larisa Bel'chikova.
    - Berezovskii, B., A postcardn.d. [December ?], An unposted postcard with a printed text and a handwritten signature. (Box 16, Folder 39)
      New Year postcard.
      Boris Berezovskii.
    - Bienek, Horst, A letter to A.Voznesenskii05.02.1988, An official typewritten letter with a handwritten signature and a posted envelope, slightly damaged. (Box 16, Folder 40)
      Horst Bienek.; Bayerische Akademie der Schönen Künste.
    - Bill, A letter to A.Voznesenskii04.16.2002, A handwritten letter on "Grand Hotel Europe" stationery, 1 page, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 41)
    - Bitov, A., A letter to A.Voznesenskii03.02.1995, A handwritten letter, 1 page, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 42)
      Andrei [?] Bitov; Zoia Boguslavskaia; Evgenii [Evgeny] Kolobov; Arkadii [?] Vaksberg.
    - Bochelov, A., Letters to A.Voznesenskii09.13.1993; n.d., Two handwritten letters, one of them with typewritten poems on the other side, 2 pages, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 43)
      A letter and several poems by Aleksei Bochelov. Thirty leaves of poetry mentioned in the letter are missing.
      Aleksei Bochelov.
    - Bochkareva, L. [?], A postcard to A.Voznesenskii and Z.Boguslavskaia11.07.1996, A handwritten postcard, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 44)
      Zoia Boguslavskaia.
    - Bogdanova, Iu., A letter to A.Voznesenskii 12.25.2000, A handwritten letter, 1 page, and an envelope with a handwritten draft made by A.Voznesenskii on the other side, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 45)
      A letter, an envelope and a draft of a poem by A.Voznesenskii (illegible). The poems by Iulia Bogdanova mentioned in the letter are missing.
      Iulia Bogdanova; I.L.Volgin; Vladimir Nuzov.
    - Boiko, V.P., A letter to A.Voznesenskii 12.21.1995, A typewritten letter with handwritten signatures, 1 page, damaged. (Box 16, Folder 46)
      Vitalii Boiko.
    - Bojars, G., An invitation08.17.2001, A typewritten letter with a handwritten addition and several handwritten drafts of poems made by A.Voznesenskii on the other side. (Box 16, Folder 47)
      An invitation letter and several drafts of poems by A.Voznesenskii (illegible).
      Gundars Bojars.
    - Bondarenko, N., A postcard to A.Voznesenskii and Z.Boguslavskaian.d. [Dec 2001 ?], A handwritten postcard. (Box 16, Folder 48)
      Natalia Bondarenko; Zoia Boguslavskaia.